<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of Spain or, an epitome of their virtues and vices.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B18917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E.2109[2]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868919</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868919</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121276</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B18917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121276)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 241:E2109[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of Spain or, an epitome of their virtues and vices.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 93, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Brooke at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a four page publisher's advertisement at end.</note>
                  <note>Verso of final leaf bears printer's device.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF SPAIN: Or, An EPITOME OF Their Virtues and Vices.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Adeo ſunt multa, loquacem </l>
               <l>Ut laſſare queant Fabium —</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Brooke</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1660.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Nathaniel Brooke, featuring an angel holding a large feather or quill</figDesc>
               <p>N B</p>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is lately publiſht an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht Piece, <hi>viz. Englands</hi> Worthies, in <hi>47</hi> ſelect Lives of the moſt eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, from <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> till theſe late times. A Piece worth peruſal, By <hi>William VVinſtanley</hi> Gent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THis handful of my Gleanings I have here ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, and if you judge them worth the gathering, take them, and welcome: if not, leave them, and there's no hurt done; For my own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, I hold it leſs criminal
<pb facs="tcp:121276:4"/>to ſport away the tedious houres with the dalliance of my Pen, than to live be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted with black Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Yet as I am not of <hi>Heraclitus</hi> his humour, to whine away my dayes; no more am I of <hi>Democritus</hi> his temper, to laugh out my time; but now and then to unbend my ſelf with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate relaxation, is my ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute temper and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Semel in anno ridet Apollo:</hi> The God of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is merry once a year, and why may not I? there is no reaſon to the contrary in my judgement, eſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:121276:4"/>ſince that no man I preſume, wil be offended at my mirth, unleſs he be a Spaniard: Now how it may move his admirable choller, I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together inſenſible, yet I am confident, if he be but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſo much patience as to peruſe it, he will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly like ſome, and that is as much as I can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expect or deſire: I have here painted them with Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Wooll, ſet them forth in their own colours, as far as lay within the compaſs of my power and ſo ſmall a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume.</p>
            <p>As for my labor herein, I
<pb facs="tcp:121276:5"/>much deteſt ſo ſickly an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, as to overwean my ſelf with a conceipt of my own Work; but if the truly judicious, who are ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a clear per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicacity, and a milde cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhall courteouſly receive it, I am crown'd: But if any left-handed <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> (who compel the Pen men of this Age, as they did the ancient Comoedians, to make uſe of Apologies in lieu of Prologues) ſhall ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterly accept what is vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily and kindly offered to their ſurvey, I onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that they may be endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:121276:5"/>with that other mute qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of the <hi>Pythagore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, viz.</hi> Silence.</p>
            <p>As for the miſtakes that I may here be accuſed of, if convinced of them, I will ingenuouſly confeſs them, and doubt not of pardon, ſince I have ſo good a Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the eye of any that are but moderately courteous, as my own infancy in reſpect of maturity of judgement. Beſides, this will plead my excuſe, the pureſt eye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcern its own blemiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, unleſs by reflection; the Moon hath her macula's or ſpots; <hi>Venus</hi> had her mole,
<pb facs="tcp:121276:6"/>and all perſons their failings, therfore for me to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted no faults, had been to put off man</p>
            <p>But if any in the proca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of ignoble Envy (oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned uſually by a deſpair of Imitation) continue to be farther contumelious, I ſhall paſs it by, knowing that a little aſſumed Soloeciſme will ſerve my turn; and I with a kinde of deaf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt will paſs by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of their obſtreperous clamor, undiſturb'd. Thus you have my reſolution, and now I have no more to do, but bid you</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121276:6"/>
            <head>THE <hi>CHARACTER</hi> OF SPAIN.</head>
            <p>TIs Nature's Sweating-tub, a Neſt of Wolves, the very Seat of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Famine, a place where never any <hi>Lotus</hi> grew; for be confident no perſon that ever travell'd thither, deſired to make it his place of reſidence; or when once paſt her bounds, was ever prompted by his fancy to a ſecond Viſit; for whoſoever goes thither may be ſaid <hi>to come out of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121276:7"/>Gods bleſſing into the warm Sun,</hi> who is too too prodigal of his Beams here, which makes the Soyl barren, and but a deſart, if compared to her neighbors, being like a Libbards skin, here a ſpot, and there a ſpot inhabited, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with huge Mountains and high Hills, which forc't a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man into this expreſſion of her, <hi>Beati qui ſterilitatem non vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ſed crediderunt:</hi> Happy are they that were never ſo unhappy as to ſee the ſterility of <hi>Spain,</hi> but to believe it onely. 'Tis an excellent Countrey to travel in, for you ſhall ſcarce meet with Meat for money, but Sawce good ſtore, nor an Inne to entertain you; for the Maſter and the Mule uſually lodge together, and the latter perhaps meets with better fare then the former.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121276:7"/>
            <p>As for the Natives, and firſt their Sovereign, he boaſts that he hath the Sun for his Creſt; but 'tis certain that moſt of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects bear the Moon creſcent, for all the ſtrict Confinement of their Wives: Pride, Haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Ambition, accompanied with an imaginary conceit of their own peculiar <hi>Grandeza,</hi> are the Ingredients that uſually go to the compoſition of a Spaniard; ſo that it is hard to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Countrey, or the mindes of the Inhabitants are moſt aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and mountainous. They are <hi>Saturnine,</hi> dull, ſlow, melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and altogether ſpeculative, aiming at no other <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> then Contemplation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out afterwards directing or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it upon any ſervile, inferior, or mechanick work or employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121276:8"/>ſo that you ſhall finde few natural Spaniards of any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Trade, as Shoemakers, Taylors, Coblers, Joyners, Inn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, or the like; for which I call all Travellers to witneſs that go into <hi>Spain,</hi> and return offended, becauſe they finde no Ale-houſes or Inns upon the way as they do in other Countreys, ſo that they are compell'd to be their own Providores, and carry Victuals in their bags, and Wine in their bottles; for they delight infinitely in their imagin'd <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deza,</hi> outward appearances and honor, not at all regarding their private intereſt, ſo that they can but create unto themſelves the opinion and eſteem of the world; and if they want good Apparel, and biting penury nips them, they will faſt two or three days for a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121276:8"/>handſom Cloak, or a ſtarch'd Ruff, and then ſtrut it abroad in ſtate; ſo deliberately do they meaſure their way, as if they ſaid a <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> or an <hi>Ave Maria</hi> between every ſtep, and if he be ſo far ſtimulated by that Tyrant <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,</hi> that he muſt vend his clothes to buy him food, he will firſt part with his Shirt, becauſe that with his Doublet &amp; Ruff he covers the want of it; then if his needs increaſe, off goes his Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet, covering his body with his Cloak; next his Sword; after that his Ruff, and laſt of all his Cloak, till he has never a one left to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his pride and knavery, and this is their method which exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies prompts them to. His pride, when reduced to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extent of poverty, <hi>viz.</hi> beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, is infamous; for he will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121276:9"/>never confeſs that neceſſity, but ſome caſualty or misfortune com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd him to it; as, that he was forced to cloath himſelf in theſe deſpicable weeds to preſerve his life, and his honor: and thus to play the Fryar Mendicant, when he craves your charity, it ſhall be in theſe or the like terms, May it pleaſe you Sir, to do ſome courteſie for a diſtreſſed Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liero, that hath deſerted his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive countrey for ſuch and ſuch a miſchance, and been conſtrained to ſhew himſelf in this misbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming garb; and when you are certified of the quality of the perſon that craves your Alms (as long it will not be) you will think your ſelves happy in relieving ſo noble a perſon as I am: and if perchance he that hears him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands who he is? he will reyly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121276:9"/>The Nephew to ſome Earl, or Duke, or Brother to the Admiral of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and that ſome famous Princeſs being enamored with him, he privily conveyed her out of her Fathers houſe in mans ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel; which Plot being diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by her Parents, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to abſent himſelf from the place of his nativity, and live thus unknown, till by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his friends he were redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to his priſtine condition: Beſides, he will boaſt of fifteen or twenty thouſand Crowns <hi>per annum,</hi> beſides eight Baronies, and if the perſon beſtows ſome ſmall piece of money on him, he throwes it contemptibly in the Donor's face, but afterwards lookes for it very calmly and peaceably on the ground, and when he ha's found it, ha's the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121276:10"/>grace to put up a <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> or ſend up ſome ſhort Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the proſperity and good ſucceſs of his Benefactor. Nor do the females come ſhort of them in pride or arrogancy, which may be ſufficiently evinced by this enſuing Relation that <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clay</hi> in his <hi>Euphormio</hi> affords me. 'Tis a ſtory of a poor miſerable Spaniſh woman, that coming with her family (her three ſonnes I mean) to beg of a French Shoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, he being compaſsionate told her, he would eaſe her of her charge, and take one of her ſons from her, and make him of his own profeſsion, that ſo he might be able to get a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, whereby he might main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf handſomly: She with a great deal of indignation replied, O Sir, God forbid I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121276:10"/>ſhould caſt away my childe on a ſtranger, of ſo mechanick a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion as yours is; who knows, but in time he may come to be Viceroy of <hi>Naples,</hi> or <hi>Mexico.</hi> So horribly are they puft up with the timpany of pride, that they are the greateſt enemies under the ſun to their own preferment: Go but into their <hi>Caſa de Locos,</hi> or Bedlam, and you ſhall hear one cry, <hi>I will be King;</hi> another, <hi>I am Emperor;</hi> and a third, <hi>I am Pope:</hi> all which verifies our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Proverb, <hi>That which is bred in the bone, will ne're out of the fleſh.</hi> Nay, their pride is ſo infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, that it is grown common, even to a Proverb, indebted to them for being ſo; for they have a vaporing ſaying of themſelves in point of valour, <hi>Un Eſpannol ſon quatro Diables en Francia.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121276:11"/>One Spaniard can act the part of four devils in <hi>France.</hi> And when <hi>Mendoza</hi> was Ambaſſadour in <hi>France,</hi> he would often break out into this prophane Oſtentation; <hi>Dios es Poderoſo en Cielo, y Don Felipe en Tierra:</hi> God bears ſway in Heaven, and King <hi>Philip</hi> on Earth: So daringly preſumptious are they, as to make God their fellow-creature. Nay, your <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonical Caſtillians</hi> will not ſtick to ſay, <hi>Un Eſpannol vale quatre Tudeſcos, tres Franceſes, y dos Italianos.</hi> One Spaniard is worth four Germans, three French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and two Italians. So ſelf-conceited are they of their own imaginary dignity and deſerts, that they judge no Nation fit to come in competition with them. I will borrow a Story of one of our rarely accompliſh'd Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121276:11"/>concerning a Caſtilian Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitain, who uſed to expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this enſuing maner: When I deſcend into my ſelf, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template my moſt horrible ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible terribility, I can hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain my ſelf within my ſelf: Theſe Breeches that I wear are ftuſt with Capitains Beards, and the Muſtacho's of French Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals; my Pillow is filled with Amazonian hair, my Cuſhion is made of a Turban taken off of the Grand Sultan's head, my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlet is the skin of the Nemean Lion that <hi>Hercules</hi> ſlew, my Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains are made up of Colours and Enſigns taken in divers Battels: When I march into the fields, I commonly carry two Drums, as Pendents at my ears; I am lull'd aſleep by the noiſe of Trumpets, and braſs Kettles; and <hi>Perillus</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:121276:12"/>his Bull ſtrecht along, ſerves me for a Pillow: I was born in the moneth of <hi>Mars,</hi> who was then the predominant Planet, and Aſcendant: I came into the world about break of day; <hi>Sol</hi> himſelf then ſuffered an Eclipſe, <hi>Jove</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> hid themſelvs, and <hi>Cynthia</hi> withdrew her horns for fear; that morning it rained blood; the ſtreams of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Rivers turn'd red; <hi>Mongibel</hi> and <hi>Strombola</hi> belch'd forth more fire then ordinarily: Near the place I was nurft in, there was a Den of Lions, that I might be mur'd to their roaring; and one time my mother cauſed a young Cub to be ſlain, on purpoſe to feed me with the blood thereof. To conclude, I am that invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, tranſcendent, great Capitain <hi>Baſiliſco Eſpheramonte,</hi> Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſimo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121276:12"/>of all the Militia of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi> I am he that uſeth to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Mountains, breathe Whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>windes, ſpit Targets, and ſweat Quick-ſilver: I believe all the Notaries in <hi>Biſcay,</hi> in three years ſpace cannot caſt up thoſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Atchievements, which I the Scourge of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of Pagans, and Peopler of Church-yards, have performed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would not any one imagine that <hi>Ovids</hi> ghoſt were rambled hither, and by a Pythagorean Metempſychoſis tranſmigrated into this Perſon, all that oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this conjecture is onely this, that the one writ in undigeſted rough proſe, and the other in ſoft ſweet verſe, this modern, hath quite out-fabled the ancient <hi>Ovid. Thraſo</hi> himſelf where he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121276:13"/>intervives, durſt not come in competition with this <hi>Bragadocio</hi> Caſtilian, ſuch a piece of prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſelf-conceitedneſs as this, the world ne're heard of. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrange kind of temper diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepant from all Nations they have, and that is this, as great an argument of their haughtineſs, as any of the preceding If any one ſhould demand an account in a ſtrange Countrey concerning any of the Natives, though never ſo mean, nay the ſon of a Cobler, he will reply, And is't poſſible, ſir, that you ſhould not know that Cavalier? Did you never hear of him? And all this nay more, though he be but one of their ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bak't Peaſants I dare lay a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger there is not a Child in the City or Kingdome five years old, but knows him, at leaſt, if he be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121276:13"/>ſprung of noble Patents. You ſhall therefore underſtand, Sir, (then he begins to be the falſe Herald of his forged fame) that he is Son to the <hi>Maggioraſco</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and one of the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble families that <hi>Spain</hi> can boaſt of, and there are many that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently pronounce him ſecond Coſin to King <hi>Philip:</hi> yet doth he go diſguſed in theſe weeds, that he may be undiſcerned by the ſearching eye of the vulgar: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides I muſt engage you to ſilence in this buſineſs, for if the King ſhould be ſenſible in the leaſt of his reſidence here, he would take it hainouſly that he did not alight at Court aſſoon as he arrived: But he that will diſcourſe of all particulars on this ſubject, muſt neceſſarily ſwell into a volume, wherefore I will wind all up
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121276:14"/>upon a ſmall bottom. Now for the nature of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> they are compoſed of fancy, and an affected gravity, under which lurks ſtore of arrogancy, you ſhall have one of a dunghil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brood ſtand on tip-toe, twerling his Muſtachos ſay, <hi>Voto a tal io ſoy tan burno ce mo el Rey Don Felipe,</hi> I ſwear by <hi>Jupiter Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that I am in as good a condition as King <hi>Philip;</hi> nor will ſome of them ſcruple the ſaying, that they will walk arm'd in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, but 'tis to be feared they are no birds of Paradiſe, and ſo there is very little probability of of their neſtling there. You ſhall ſee ſome of their Dons pacing of it with abundance of gravity, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viron'd with a croud of Servitors, or more properly, vaſſalls, two before him, one holds his hat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121276:14"/>occaſion, another his cloak, if it chance to rain, another carries a clout to rub his Ginnet whileſt he is at Maſs, another a Curry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb to kemb his Mane, and all theſe when they come home, will be content with a cruſt of bread, and a radiſh apiece for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt. They have a ſaying of the French (between whom there is a very ſtrange antipathy, and that irreconcilable too; <hi>Al primer impetu ſon mas que hombres, y de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpues menos que mugeres.</hi> Their firſt onſet manifeſts them more then men, but their laſt leſs then women. But they to requite their kindneſs, have an ill-favor'd ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, <hi>That the Spaniards in point of true active valor, are but bearded women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to their habit and garb, they uſually go cloſe buttoned,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121276:15"/>nor will they unbutton though fire fall from heaven. Their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is very cloſe, as if they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that ſaying in the ſacred Code, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> All things are bare neckt to God. He uſually wears that upon his arms, which others do on their thighs, <hi>viz.</hi> long ſleeves, and ſhort breeches: beſides, he wears his ſtockings ſo cloſe and ſtreight to his Leg, that you cannot take hold of them with a pair of pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: As for their geſture in the ſtreet, if there be a company, they march two by two, as if they went in proceſsion to ſome Saint, or Lady, and that ſo ſlowly, that you would judge them to be newly recovered of a Quartan-Ague; and 'tis beyond the power of whip or ſtaff to quicken their pace. As for their ſpeech, they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121276:15"/>are ſo helliſhly ambitious, as to ſay that when God forbad <hi>Adam</hi> eating of the tree of knowledge, he ſpoke in Spaniſh, ſuch is their imperiouſneſs and arrogancy; but I am an enemy to tediouſneſs, eſpecially whileſt I am under the name of a Character; therefore to ſome other particulars.</p>
            <p>And firſt let's make a Paſs at the Jeſuite, that plays the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavilian</hi> both in Church and State, thoſe grand Supporters of the Spaniſh Crown, which made a Burgundian Gentleman ſay, <hi>Un Eſpagnol ſans ſon Jeſuite eſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me un Perdrix ſans Orange.</hi> A Spaniard without a Jeſuite at his elbow in conſultation, is like Powder'd-beef without muſtard. Define them we need not, ſince 'tis done already to our hands by <hi>Alexander Hays,</hi> one of their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121276:16"/>own Order, and 'tis this; <hi>Jeſuita eſt omnis home:</hi> They are <hi>Pluto's</hi> prime Agents, that labor tooth and nayl to people his infernal Territories, and adde Vaſſals to his gloomy majeſty. No perſons have been greater Incendiaries, or <hi>Boutefeux,</hi> then theſe Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical <hi>Groteſco's;</hi> they uſher in all Quarrels, Contentions, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and Sciſſures, both in Church and State. They are the <hi>Umbra</hi> of the Nobility, inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aſſociates, that follow them as a ſhadow doth the bodies, which is the reaſon of the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Legacies that are conferr'd upon them, yet they are like thoſe little animals <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>qua mordent, &amp; non ſentiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> For whereſoever they get footing or entertainment, they prejudice by inſenſible encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121276:16"/>though the party ſhall not judge himſelf hurt, or damaged in the leaſt. And as to their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Inquiſition, if you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon a Diſpute concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Doctrine held by the Roman Church, they will retort with a Syllogiſm of Hemp, or Fire, which is far more harſh then one in <hi>Barbara,</hi> or <hi>Baroco,</hi> and fitter for devils then men. And though they are ſo much in eſteem with the Pope, yet are they maligned and flouted at by the vulgar, as appears by the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quils no leſs various, then inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and tart, that are beſtowed on them in every place, which is apparent to any one that is but a mean Hiſtorian. When they firſt negotiated in <hi>France</hi> for footing in <hi>Paris,</hi> they were askt, whether they were <hi>Seculares,</hi> or <hi>Regulares?</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:121276:17"/>and replied, <hi>Tales, Quales,</hi> ſuch and ſuch, which remain; upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord a Nick-name to them even to this very day. But what the ſubject beſtowed on them with the tongue, they fetcht out of their Soveraign's teeth (King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth I mean) they began to take a courſe that he might be hit in the teeth with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, by endeavoring to beat them all out; for a young Jeſuite green in growth, but old in vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, ſtabb'd him in the mouth, though it happened with the loſs of one onely tooth; whereupon the King ſaid merrily, <hi>Falloit il que les Jeſuites fuſſent convanicus par ma bouche?</hi> Muſt they needs be convinced by my mouth? Hereupon they were command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to depart the Kingdom by ſuch a day, and a new Stone-Gallows
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121276:17"/>erected before the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace gate for the execution of the Offender; but the King out of fear (ſo much do they awe the Scepter) removed it; Hereupon one ſung ingeniouſly to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sire, ſi vous voulez du tout a l'advenir,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>De L'Aſſaſsin</hi> Chaſtel <hi>oſter le ſou venir;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oſtant la Pyramide, &amp; l'Arreſt qui le touche,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qu'on vous remette donc une dent dans la bouche.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Taught to ſpeak Engliſh thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Great Prince, if for the future you will ſave</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chaſtel</hi> th'Aſſaſſine, that noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Knave;</l>
               <l>And pull the Gibbet down, to purge the ſtain,</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121276:18"/>
               <l>Let him put in your mouth the tooth again.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But they finding themſelves too much abuſed by the impoſition of that ſcandalous Title on them of <hi>Tales, Quales,</hi> (as they judg'd it) were ſo prophane as to call themſelves <hi>Socios Jeſu</hi> ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Aſſociates of Chriſt (da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring villains, that rank themſelves in the ſame degree with their Redeemer) yet in the ſacred pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges we read but of one that was called <hi>Chriſt's Companion,</hi> and that was <hi>Judas:</hi> this muſt needs be in their own judgement <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum per pejus,</hi> they have well mended the matter; for they were their own God-fathers, and did rebaptize themſelves contrary to the Canons of their own Church, for they allow not a ſecond Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and that with a far more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121276:18"/>ignominious (as it falls out) though truer appellation. 'Twas their ſophiſtical equivocation that cauſed that Clauſe to be inſerted in the Oath of Supremacy in <hi>England, without mental reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Nay, the Great Turk on the <hi>Aſian</hi> ſhore, baniſhed them out of <hi>Pera</hi> near <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> upon the relation that Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeths</hi> Ambaſſadors made of their impiety and inhumanity. Nay the <hi>Venetians,</hi> though birds of the ſame feathers, and both feathers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagle, drove this ridiculous and raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bird clear out of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of their Dominions, ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible were they of the horrible out-rages that are uſually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by them; for there is no maſſacre how inhumane ſoever, but either they kindle the fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121276:19"/>or afford the fuel. One of their notorious Machiavilian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, though fruſtrated, was hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched for our deſtruction, <hi>viz.</hi> in Eighty Eight, when they came with their invincible Armado (as they ſtyled it) but we re-baptized it in our Brittiſh Seas, the <hi>Vinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Armado,</hi> for there it was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmed, deſtroyed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed. They made a wood of our Seas, through the number of their Ships, every Galeon like the Trojan Horſe, having armed men in the womb of it, with all ſorts of inſtruments for torture; among ſome whereof, there were found long Knives, with this ſcandalous Superſcription, <hi>To cut the throats of Hereticks,</hi> and yet not a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Complotter in all this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, but muſt be canonized for a Saint; as if it lay within the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121276:19"/>compaſs of his power that ſits in the Porphiry-chair to exempt men from the puniſhment due to thoſe ſins, which the Almighty hath ordain'd for ſuch helliſh Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors; but it is to be hoped, that their Plots, like the form in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which they reduced their ſhips, <hi>viz.</hi> a Moon creſcent, may ever prove a Moon in the wane, and that the feathers of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Eagle may molt away, till it become a ridiculous bird, and become the object and ſubject of laughter to all her Neighboring Nations.</p>
            <p>But the Maſter-piece of all, was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Plo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>mous a nature, that it ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er to be (as one of our gowned Gentlemen ſaith) <q rend="inline">A piece hammer'd in Hell by a Conclave of Cacodaemons, than
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121276:20"/>traced by humane invention. A ſulpherous Mine prepared and fitted with that Artifice, that with one ſnuff it ſhould have blown up to the Clouds, and made but a ſquib of that mighty Aſſembly, with many thouſands of innocent ſouls beſides: <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Sovereign Monarch, with his Royal Conſort, and Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Iſſue; Root and Rind, Stem and Stock, Bud and Bloſſom, had all been blaſted, and that in a moment.</q> 
               <hi>Oculi intuitu,</hi> in the very twinckling of an eye, and all our ſtately Fabricks and Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures had bin turn'd into aſhes: But before I ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cruelty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſelf (Reader) for trag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, leſt the ſuddenneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of the Fact aſtoniſh your
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121276:20"/>Apprehenſion; and here think of nothing but Graves, Tombs and Epitaphs, Flakes of Fire, Cracks of Thunder, Aſtma's, and Veſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio's; for here is a Plot that Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory is at a <hi>non-plus</hi> to parallel. O learned Jeſuite! Haſt thou hammered upon the Forge of thy accurſed Brain (for indeed he was the Blackſmith of this diabolical Stratagem) a Cruelty, as horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as unheard of: not the <hi>Ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liac's</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> their own <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> the <hi>Machiavils</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Gowries</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> or <hi>Oneals</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor any other vicious or deſperate mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal yet found out: 'Tis plain that in this they intended to out-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil the grand Elector of <hi>Erebua,</hi> if 'twere poſſible: A cruelty that tranſcends all Roman ſtory, far beyond that of <hi>Catiline, Brutus,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121276:21"/>or <hi>Lucius Scaevola.</hi> Preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous villains! that dare ſend ſouls to Heaven before the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and make companions for <hi>Elijah</hi> in his fiery Chariot. Here might you ſee theſe Pioneers dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Hell for Aſſiſtance, when Heaven had denied it them ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but at length Sennior Satan took compaſſion of their labor, and helpt them with a deſtructive invention: Herein 'tis apparent they receiv'd aſſiſtance from, and encountered with the greateſt head of the helliſh <hi>Hydra</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways except the <hi>Pope</hi>) fain would they have made our Land like the way of <hi>Medea,</hi> ſtrewed with the Limbs of her brother <hi>Abſyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus;</hi> here the arm of a Father, there the leg of a mother; here the limb of one relation, there the joynt of another, <hi>his laquens
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121276:21"/>poſitus eſt;</hi> here the gin was laid, but like ſilly Woodcocks they were enſnar'd in't themſelves.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>—<hi>Non lex eſt iuſtior ulla, </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quam necis artifices, arte perire ſuâ.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>—'Tis juſt I'le ſwear, </l>
                  <l>That they ſhould all be caught in their own ſnare.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>O rare Saints! what? Turn your Saint <hi>Peter</hi> into Saltpeter, to deſtroy us, and all we can lay claim to?
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rem, Regem, Regimen, Regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Religionem.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Religion, Subſtance, Kingdom, King,</l>
                     <l>Of all our famous Lawes the Spring.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121276:22"/>And they were prompted to all their cruelty, inhumanity, and barbariſm, by their zeal to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Sacred Lady, muſt thou be the Mantle to cover their infandous villany; the Cloak to palliate their ſtupendious cruelty? Thou that uſeſt to be clad with the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of light, muſt thou be made the Authoreſs of ſuch ſubterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean darkneſs? No, no, far be it from a rational perſon, or ſolid Chriſtian to entertain a thought ſo prejudicial and injurious to thy ſacred, incontaminated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency.</p>
            <p>But 'tis the general courſe of theſe helliſh Machiavilians, not to ſuffer Vice to appear upon the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121276:22"/>ſtage in its ugly hew, and native deformity, leſt it ſhould deter all perſons from it, but they mask or cover it with the vayl of virtue. And farther to ſhew that the edge of their Satanical invention is not yet blunted, and manifeſt their choller ſtill againſt us, they keep near the Fifth of <hi>November</hi> a Day of Execration, wherein they curſe Heretickes, as they term us; in which they approach neareſt of any, and reſemble moſt of all the rebellious Jew, that crucified our Saviour; who on the twelfth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> had their time of Execration, wherein they cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> and the Romane Soldiers for demoliſhing their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Nor is their malice and envy glutted or ſatisfied with <hi>Europian</hi> blood, but they muſt ſatiate their fury
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121276:23"/>with the Indian too: and though they pretend that their right to both Indies, is right of Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that they were the firſt Detectors of it, it is queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, if not abſolutely falſe; for <hi>Pliny</hi> the Carthaginian was the firſt Diſcoverer of <hi>India,</hi> by croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Equinoctial twice; nor were the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> unknown to <hi>Plate:</hi> Beſides, a greater evidence then the forementioned, that the Spaniards were not the firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverers of <hi>America,</hi> is this, That there was a Welch Epitaph found at their firſt landing there, upon <hi>Madoc</hi> a Brittiſh Prince; who, as 'tis ſuppoſed, made an eſcape to ſave himſelf from the fury of the Saxons in <hi>England,</hi> and put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a Barque to the fortune of the Sea, and ſo landed in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica.</hi> And 'tis farther confirmed,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121276:23"/>that the old Brittiſh or Weclh were there, from the variety of Brittiſh words retain'd among them in their language even at this very day. But whether they were the firſt Diſcoverers or no; it is obſerv'd, that thoſe vaſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſhe tranſports thence thrive little, by reaſon of that ocean of human (though ſavage) blood the Spaniard ſpilt there; never did any nation phlebotomize an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſo inhumanely as they did, in ſo much that it is affirmed by ſome, (and that groundedly too) that the blood they ſpilt would over-poiſe all the gold they ever fetcht from thence, if it were counter-ballanced; and as that vaſt Treaſure was firſt gained by the effuſion of much blood, ſo hath it been ominous and fatal ever ſince, &amp; conſum'd in blood;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121276:24"/>for moſt of the Combuſtions and Diſſentions of the Occidental World have bin fed and fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them; nay, which is more prejudicial to it, in point of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> by theſe Mines and means, furniſheth the major part of his Enemies with Arms defenſive and offenſive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, the leaſt part of the treaſure remaining among them; for moſt of their current Coyn is Copper, ſo that we may ſay, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Engliſh Proverb, <hi>Who is worſe ſhod than the Shooe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers wife?</hi> In ſo much that we may compare her (and that very fitly) to the Arcadian Aſs; who, though laden with Gold, yet browzeth upon Thiſtles.</p>
            <p>As to their Cruelty in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Conqueſt, it was ſo inhuman, that the relation thereof would
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121276:24"/>ſtagger the belief of a Chriſtian, were there not a general conſent among all Hiſtoriographers of the hainouſneſs thereof. Such horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Murthers and Maſſacres did they commit, that I bluſh to ſtain my paper with their relation; for 'tis affirmed by ſome (and thoſe of no mean credit) that in the ſpace of forty five years, there were above ten millions of ſouls deſtroyed in the New World, as they are pleaſed to call it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe great numbers that died by working in the Mines, officiating like Aſſes, Oxes, and Mules; ſome of them being loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with burthens on their back of one hundred and ſixty pound weight, carrying them three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles, ſometimes more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe that periſhed in the water with fiſhing for Pearl, in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121276:25"/>obedience to their inſulting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, being dieted on purpoſe by them for that work with courſe Bisket, and dry edible commodities, to make them fit for that work: poor ſlender fare for ſuch hard and ſlaviſh labor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: They ſcorn'd, it ſeems, to murther by retail, but <hi>Caligula</hi> like, their glutton blades muſt be imbrued in the bowels of a whole Nation. Nay farther, they made a ſport and recreation of their inhumanity and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm; for they hunted them with dogs, as if they have been beaſts of the Game, and not their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-creatures; to confirm which, there is a ſtory of an old impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Indian woman that was ſent by a Spaniard, with a Letter to the Governor of the next Town, who, when ſhe was departed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121276:25"/>about a flight ſhot off of him, he let ſlip his dog at her; which ſhe perceiving fell on her knees, and cried out, <hi>Sennor, Sennor Dog,</hi> (ſo much Spaniſh ſhe had) <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee ſpare me, for I am a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a Letter from thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to the Governor;</hi> the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate creature it ſeems moved with compaſſion at her words, and ſuppliant poſture, being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exerciſed in the rules of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and mortality than his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, took compaſsion on her, only lifting up his leg and piſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, and ſo let her depart in peace. Now the Spaniards had rendred themſelves ſo odious to thoſe Indians, by reaſon of their cruelty, that not one of a noble reſolution among them could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to hear of going to any place that they frequented, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121276:26"/>after their diſſolution, as may appear by the ſtory of one <hi>Hathu Cacico</hi> a ſtout Indian, who being to die, (for his being an Indian was crime enough to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit death, though probably no malefactor) <hi>Stat pro ratione vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas,</hi> was their Motto, <hi>Their will was their Law;</hi> who being perſwaded by a Franciſcan Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, and admoniſhed to turn Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoſique, and embrace the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſuperſtition, withal acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him with the joys of heaven, and how that he ſhould be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported thither, if he would be converted, or to ſpeak more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, perverted; whereupon he demanded of the Franciſcan whether or no there were any Spaniards in heaven? who repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yes, 'twas peopled with them: then ſaid he, I will chooſe rather
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121276:26"/>to go to Hell, then to have their company: a notable example of heathen generoſity, which might intimate unto them, they could not conquer their ſpirits, though they maſſacred their bodies. Nay <hi>Attabalipa</hi> one of their Pagan Kings being informed, That the Pope had conferr'd his kingdom upon the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> was heard to utter this as noble, as tart expreſſion, That the Pope muſt be either an egregious fool, or an uniuſt Tyrant, that durſt have the impudence to take upon him the beſtowing of other mens Right and Poſſeſſions, ſo freely and liberally to others, that had no right nor title to them.</p>
            <p>Nor were they thus ſatiated with drinking the ſavage blood of the Indians, but they muſt be ſucking the blood of the Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121276:27"/>Chriſtians too; witneſs the Tyranny of the Duke <hi>d'Alva,</hi> termed (and not undeſervedly) <hi>The Spunge of the Belgian Blood;</hi> for he made it his boaſt, and a kinde of ſportive recreation to be heard often ſaying, That he had diſpatch't to the other world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove eighteen thouſand Belgians by Fire, Water, the Rack, the Sword, and the Ax. Nor is it to be found a humour in Subjects onely, but in their Monarchs likewiſe; witneſs one of their Kings, who being diſturb'd at the divers ill Succeſſes that he had in his Politick Proceedings, ſwore he would be revenged upon the Superior Power, that hath the conduct and guidance of all mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Affairs, and therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that none of his ſubjects ſhould adore, believe in, or ſpeak
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121276:27"/>of God for ſo long time, upon pain of his utter diſpleaſure. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious wretches! that durſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Omnipotency, or venter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſingle Duel with the Deity. Now as to the Gigantick power of his Catholick Majeſty, if it be equally poiz'd in the ballance of a diſcerning judgement, it comes far ſhort of that height and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor that is uſually attributed to it; for the vaſt diſtance of his Territories, the innumerable Debts be hath contracted, (and he is infinitely indebted to the <hi>Genoeſe</hi> and others) the univerſal antipathy that is between them and all Nations in general, by reaſon of their ambition, pride, and haughtineſs, is as great an impediment and debilitating, as his Wealth is a Fortification or Aſſiſtance. And as for Juſtice,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121276:28"/>the Queen of Virtues, ſhe hath as little power there, as among any people on the ſurface of the earth, eſpecially for forreiners; for it is as facil a buſineſs to draw a ſoul out of the jaws of Hell, as to recover any thing againſt them if they graſp it once within their clutches: And if a ſtranger come to commence a Suit at Law there againſt a Spaniard, the proceſſal charges will oftentimes ſurmount the value of the thing, or right you ſue for.</p>
            <p>As for zeal, and innate valor, where ſhall you finde it among them? 'tis more rare to ſee a Duel there, then a Horſe in <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice;</hi> or to hear of a Spurrier prefer'd to a Queen; though not a Cobler or Smith among them can be ſeen without a Sword, which they wear for orament, not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121276:28"/>uſe: yet if they have receiv'd any abuſe or affront, they will be ſure to meet in the Market-place, and there draw, pretending to run furiouſly one at another, becauſe they are ſure to be parted e're they make a paſs, or can well tell how to mount their weapon; and uſually the Miniſter of Juſtice (as they call him) deprives them both of their weapons for a time, till he hath wrought a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis true, in the Conqueſt of the Weſtern World, they did atchieve ſomewhat, but it was againſt a naked, inermous enemy, who were deſtitute of all defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive or offenſive weapons; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſo ſtupid and ignorant were the poor Americans, that they took Horſe and Man to be one Aminal, born contrary to the courſe of natural production, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121276:29"/>begot of ſome infernal ſtage; which Bug-bear opinion profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated the Indian, and not the Spaniſh manhood or valor: where was the Spaniſh generoſity and nobility of ſpirit, when <hi>Goleta</hi> near <hi>Tunis</hi> was ſhamefully loſt by them, and taken by <hi>Sinan Baſſa,</hi> with five hundred Pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which hath arm'd <hi>Tunis</hi> and <hi>Algier</hi> ever ſince, and made them ſuch infamous Pyrats? I muſt confeſs, were the word of ſufficiency to combat with the ſword, or could the good conceit they have of their own magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, or the loud (though unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) Encomiums they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon themſelves, and their deſerts make them men of war, they would ſubjugate the whole univerſe, and excel all their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors in military diſcipline;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121276:29"/>but words will not gain the field, it muſt be action.</p>
            <p>As for the number of their Learned, I think they have no great quantity; <hi>Raymundus Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> is one of their famous Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, one that (like a native Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard) was very much conceited of his ability in the ſtudy of the Philoſophers Stone, or <hi>Elixir;</hi> of whom it may be ſaid, as of all others that follow that whimſie:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Et bona dilapidant omnia pro la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>How much he was eſteemed of, this enſuing Dyſtich will clearly demonſtrate.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui Lulli lapidem quaerit, quem quarere nulli</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Profuit; Hand Lullus, ſed mihi nullus erit.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>There is nothing but air in that vain fooliſh ſtudy, nothing of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121276:30"/>ſubſtance; their glowing fire doth but ſwell up their hope of gain, till the ſpirits quite expire, and ſo their fortunes die: Nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can it be expected, that they ſhould excel in any kind of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, becauſe they peruſe no vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes but their own, penn'd in their own language, and in their Univerſity Diſſertations, their <hi>Vernaculum</hi> or Mother tongue carries the greateſt ſway (which is made up of nothing, but a few ſhreds of <hi>Moriſco,</hi> and patched up with ſome old Arabick words) for they ſeldom, ſcarce once in an age, diſpute in the <hi>Roman</hi> tongue. And before we leave their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Rabble, let us have one hit more at their modern Jaſons, the Jeſuites, thoſe Clergy-men of the Golden-fleece, that devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more to Madam <hi>Moneta,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:121276:30"/>then the Lady <hi>Loretto,</hi> or the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and if we conſider their Tenets in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we ſhall finde them as erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous and diabolical, nay, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametrically contrary to Reaſon or Divinity, as their politick, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, Machiavilian Plots and Practiſes. Our Engliſh Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles makes mention of one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Garnet</hi> a Jeſuite, who being interrogated by the Earl of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham,</hi> whether or no, if any one ſhould confeſs unto him in the morning, that he had a deſign to murther the King that very ev'ning, he thought himſelf bound in conſcience to reveal it? he replied in the negative; which infernal doctrine was confirmed by <hi>Binetus</hi> the Jeſuite, in theſe words: <hi>Praeſtare Reges omnes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ire, quam ſi vel ſemel Confeſſionis
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121276:31"/>ſigillum violaretur; Regem enim humani juris Imperium ait eſſe, Confeſſionem juris divini:</hi> In Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thus: It were far better that all the Kings in the world ſhould be murthered, than that the Seal of Confeſſion ſhould be violated in the leaſt; for the dignity of a King is indebted to humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for its being; but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to Divine Inſtitution. Nay, there was a Jeſuit in <hi>France</hi> who had the impudence to belch this blaſphemy in publick, and to maintain, if there were occaſion, <hi>Si Dominus noſter Jeſus Chriſtus in terris verſaretur morti obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; aliquis ſibi in Confeſſione dixiſſet velle ſe illum occidere, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſquam Confeſſionem revaleret, paſſurum ſe, ut Chriſtus occidatur.</hi> O profane! in Engliſh thus: If our Lord and our Saviour Jeſus
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121276:31"/>Chriſt were upon the earth, and mortal, and that any one ſhould confeſs unto him that he had an intention to murther him, he would ſuffer our Saviour to be ſlain, rather then diſcloſe it. Right <hi>Judas'es,</hi> that had rather murther their Maſter than thwart their own vain traditions, and for pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick Chymaera's, that never were hatcht hitherto in any but ſuch addle pates as their own; but let them have a care leſt that they finde <hi>Judas</hi> his puniſhment, ſince they are ſo much guilty of his hainous crime. This is a more daring, nefandous piece of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, than that fictitious one of the Gigantomachy; for they do not onely aim at the dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Deity, but would, were it within the compaſs of their helliſh inventions, be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121276:32"/>as to murther him. Our moſt gracious Sovereign of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memory, King <hi>James,</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a ſeaſonable Caveat from his God-mother Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to take heed of the Spaniard; who anſwered her very ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, <hi>Se non aliud beneficium ab Hiſpano expectare, quam quod U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſi Polyphemus promiſerat, ut aliis devoratis, poſtremus degluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur.</hi> That he expected no more favour from the Spaniard, than what <hi>Polyphemus</hi> promiſed <hi>Ulyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> that all the reſt being devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it ſhould fall to his ſhare to go laſt to pot. There is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction among them, when ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by rage and fury, Prince and People, King and Kingdom, all go to rack, if it lie in their power. Now 'tis moſt certain by this <hi>Hildebrandine</hi> Jeſuitical do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121276:32"/>of their auricular Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for they open the Cabinets of Princes, and no perſons have ſuch ſure and faithful intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence as they from all parts in Chriſtendom: Beſides, there are no Eccleſiaſticks that frequent the Court, or Noblemens houſes more than they, ſo that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all the Tranſactions in Church and State in all parts of the Chriſtian world, and thereby are enabled to put themſelves in a poſture to act their damnable deſigns; yet, notwithſtanding all their ſiniſter and politick practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to ſupport the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> and defend his Holineſs, they remain but in a wavering and fluctuating condition; for the late <hi>Motus trepidationis</hi> in <hi>Naples,</hi> and that in <hi>Sicily,</hi> with the total Revolt of the <hi>Portugeſe,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121276:33"/>and the <hi>Catalonian</hi> Commotions, and thoſe vaſt Debts that they have contracted with the <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> and ſeveral other accidents that might be mentioned, hath ſo ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Spaniſh Monarchy, that ſhe continues in an anguiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ever ſince, and there is very little probability of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetlement. <hi>Decreſcit Oliva,</hi> the Olive-branches begin to wither and decay; and 'tis very much fear'd by themſelves, that ſhe will be found dead at the root ere long, if by a diligent lopping off of her ſuperfluous branches, and the careful management, and ordering of her State-Gardeners, ſhe be not revived, and made to bud and bloſſom afreſh: But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſhe will come to a ſad Cataſtrophe, if the tympany of the Spaniards pride be not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaged
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121276:33"/>and taken down: Beſides the innumerable ill ſucceſſes that ſhe hath had in all her underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, is a ſufficient argument to diſſwade her from ever believing Fortune to be her favorite; ſhe ſeem'd indeed to be in the poop, and favor King <hi>Philip,</hi> till he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a memorable Defeat at <hi>Moſtagan</hi> in <hi>Barbary,</hi> under the Conduct of <hi>Alcaudite</hi> a petty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Moriſco King; and their ill ſucceſs at <hi>Los Gelves</hi> near <hi>Tripoli,</hi> where moſt of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the Neopolitan Gallies under the Conduct of <hi>Don Alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> their Chief Commander, were ſouc'd in <hi>Thetis</hi> Powdering-tub, and made meat for Sharks and Shaddocks; which was occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the imprudence of their Leaders, when as otherwiſe they might have come off nobly, with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121276:34"/>the name of Conquerors. Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others I might mention, but I will not upbraid them too much with their infelicity: onely take this by the way, that when <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond rigg'd that numerous Fleet againſt our Land, with an abſolute intent to ruinate us, he was repuls'd by the valor of the Engliſh, with ſo much diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the whole Nation, that he paſſionately ſaid, <hi>He ſent his men to fight with men, and not with the Windes and the Sea:</hi> nay, one of their holy Conclave, in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was heard to ſay publickly, <hi>That by this very buſineſs, and the fruſtrating of their deſign God had manifeſted himſelf a Lutheran.</hi> 'Tis ſtrange methinks, noble Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, that he ſhould fight for the Hereticks againſt the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, as you term your ſelves!
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121276:34"/>Methinks you might obſerve the ſaying of your Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, (who was of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian</hi> family) and have taken his Advice a little more into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Con todo el mundo guerra,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Y puz con Ingalat jerra.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>In Engliſh thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>With all the world wage war,</l>
               <l>But ne're with <hi>England</hi> jar.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For if you do, you muſt be arm'd and quilted, and for all that may be baſted into the bargain: Be confident <hi>Sennor Eſpannol,</hi> if you come to bake in our Oven, your Cake will be dough. There's no kindling your Irons in our fire, unleſs you meane to be ſcorch't with them; but methinks you might have ſo much wit, as to take warning by our Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>The burnt childe dreads the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121276:35"/>fire;</hi> if not, as you like the play of our Brittiſn Guns, venter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another Invaſion: we have more <hi>Drakes</hi> ſtill to ſend their Fire-ſhips among you, and ſend you back to your Confines toſs'd and weather-beaten, if any of you be ſo happy as to eſcape: well make you know your heart lies in your heels, and flying is your beſt courſe; you are like to have no harbor here, a retreat is your ſafeſt refuge.</p>
            <p>Before the Embaſſage of the Conſtable of <hi>Caſtile</hi> mediating for peace with us, your prating Jeſuite had infected the common people of <hi>Spain</hi> with a falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the Engliſh were ſtrangely metamorphos'd, ſome had the faces of Hogs, ſome did reſemble Dogs, and others Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kies, ſince they forſook the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121276:35"/>Church; which they poor ſilly ſouls did really believe, till the Conſtable at his return did rectifie his Countrey-men. But conceit them ſo ſtill; but if they be Dogs, they come all of noble Sires, they are no Mungrels, but ſuch Maſtiffs as will bark you out of your wits; and ſuch Munkies they are, that if they make but a face at you, that's enough to ſcare a whole Legion of you; and if you are ſo incredulous as not to believe it, try once more, and then judge according to your ſucceſs. When the Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween our late bleſſed Sovereign of happy memory (though of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy fortune) and the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> was in agitation, the Nobility of <hi>England</hi> that were dieted at the King's Table, and attended by the Spaniards, were
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121276:36"/>not ſo meanly bred, as to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with your poor Cates, which made them break out into many ſcoffing expreſſions touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the barrenneſs of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alſo at the vanity of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Proceſſions. And <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chee</hi> the Kings Jeſter being at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and admitted one day to ſee his Catholick Majeſty at Dinner, ſtrutted and walk'd up and down, talking and mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, askt what he ſaid? which an Interpreter there preſent made anſwer, He ſaith that King <hi>James</hi> his Maſter did reſemble God Almighty moſt of any King in the world. And he demanding the reaſon, was anſwered, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that God had but one ſon, and he ſent him to be crucified among the Jews, ſo the King of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121276:36"/>
               <hi>England</hi> had but one ſon, and he ſent him to be crucified among the Spaniards: a notable ſaying to check them for their accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med cruelty and barbariſm, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in this he prov'd but a fooliſh, and falſe Prophet, and to our joy and comfort it fell out quite contrary.</p>
            <p>There happened one day a very facetious, quipping paſſage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt King <hi>Philip</hi> and a Veteran Capitain, that had ſerved him a long time in the <hi>Belgian</hi> Wars, who being deferr'd by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of State, was reſolved to find out his Majeſty himſelf, who was then at the <hi>Eſcurial,</hi> and as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune would have it, hunting; where mounted on his Mule, and meeting the King ſingle in the field, the King began to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Diſcourſe with him: firſt,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121276:37"/>demanding who he was? The blunt Soldier judging him to be ſome private Nobleman, related the whole ſtory to him, recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how that he had ſerved <hi>Don Philip</hi> many years in the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and that now he was come to demand a remuneration: The King anſwered, Doth <hi>Don Philip</hi> owe you any thing of your lawful pay? No, ſaid the Capitain: then replied the King, I am clearly of opinion, that he will ſcarce give you any thing ſince he hath ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied you in your arrears, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally becauſe he is infinitely indebted, and hath many deſigns to put forward; at which the Capitain broke off abruptly, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Pues que me beſe la mula en el culo:</hi> Then let him, kiſs my Mule in the tayl; and ſo was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding away, but the King call'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121276:37"/>him back, and ask'd him what Petition he had made, or what courſe he had taken for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? He told him that he had often attended the Councel of State, and War, with his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, but was never the near, nor could he ever procure the ſight of his Majeſty there, nor elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. Very good, ſaid the King, the Councel ſits to morrow, and I ſhall be there preſent, for I have an Office there; wherefore if you come I ſhall procure your entrance, and then you may make your Addreſs to <hi>Don Philip</hi> in perſon. The King the very next day did preſide himſelf in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and gave ſtrict order, that if ſuch a perſon, deſcribing him of ſuch a name, (for that he had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him by their Conference) ſhould chance to be at the door,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121276:38"/>he ſhould be admitted: the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitain coming, and having enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſeeing the Councel bare, and knowing this to be the King with whom he had private diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe yeſterday, he was not much out of countenance: Immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Philip</hi> ask't him, whether he remembered the diſcourſe that was between them in the field? Yes Sir, replies the Capitain; then, ſaid he, you cannot forget what you ſaid: <hi>That if the King would not reward you, he might kiſs your Mule in the breech:</hi> Sir, replied he, <hi>Seno lo dicho, dichio, mi Mula eſta debaxo a la puerta:</hi> What I ſaid, I ſaid, and Mule ſtands below at the back gate: The King was not at all diſturb'd but gave him his hand to kiſs, and caus'd him to be nobly reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He had now quite forgot his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121276:38"/>uſual expreſſion to thoſe that came to requeſt any thing of him, <hi>Si a todos los que me piden daria, preſto pediria yo:</hi> If I ſhould give to every one that puts up a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to me, I might ſoon come to beg my ſelf. Well done Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitain, hug thy blunt Genius, it was that procur'd thy reward, not his bounty; who, though a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, had ſoon ſent thee pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a curb, hadſt thou not gone contrary to the common courſe of men who with ſo much ſubmiſſiveneſs did uſe to petition his Majeſty; well ſaid down-right: hereafter cry, <hi>hang Complements,</hi> and ſwear, <hi>Complementum</hi> is but <hi>complete mentiri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now ſince we are upon ſo ſlovingly a ſubject, let's expatiate upon a ſtory that is ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin to this, which happened at a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121276:39"/>ſolemn Convention of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his Catholick Majeſty, and his moſt Chriſtian of <hi>France,</hi> with thouſands of the Nobility of both Nations; who being all bare, and the Pope ready to mount, to ride in Proceſſion, one of theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs holding the Stirrop on foot, and the other his Saddle, both uncovered, and kiſſing his Pantofle. The King of <hi>France</hi> his Jeſter ſpying it, and taking it into conſideration, ſtreight en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to make through the Croud, crying out aloud, <hi>Make room, make room;</hi> at which the multitude being aſtoniſhed, askt him what was the matter? what forc't him to theſe loud exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? <hi>O!</hi> replied he, <hi>I'le be gone to</hi> Paris. Why? your reaſon? <hi>O!</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if the Pope make ſo great a Monarch as my Maſter kiſs his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121276:39"/>Toe, hee'l make me kiſs his Breech by and by, therefore I'le be gone.</hi> He it ſhould ſeem was not mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſalute his Apoſtolick rump; nor did he much fancy the kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his Toe, but if he had been compell'd to't, he would have gone near to have ſhown his Holineſs as ſnappiſh a trick as the Ambaſſadors dog did, that almoſt bit it off: But we'l have no more of theſe whimſies, leſt ſome Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick or other ſhould ſay, that this Treatiſe is fit for nothing but to make cul-paper, that is, <hi>ad ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtergendum podicem.</hi> Methinks I hear 'em cry, fie, fie, therefore I muſt give o're. And now let's pitch upon ſome more cleanly ſubiect, if we can hit on any, ſure we ſhall finde out one at length, and yet it muſt be of that King <hi>Philip</hi> before mention'd, who had
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121276:40"/>erected a <hi>Pyramis</hi> in the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place at <hi>Santo Domingo</hi> (where our famous Swimmer <hi>Drake</hi> was, who took and plundred it) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was found this Motto:</p>
            <q>—<hi>Non ſufficit Orbis:</hi>
            </q>
            <p>One world was too narrow to confine the ſpacious ſoul of <hi>Don Philip.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Aeſtuat infeliae anguſto limite mundi:</hi>
            </q>
            <p>His capacious and moſt ample Majeſty did ſweat again for want of room in this narrow World; yet notwithſtanding his proud boaſting (but that you know is like a Spaniard) he was overcome by an Army of poor inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able creatures, ſilly worms; for <hi>Herod</hi>-like, he periſhed <hi>morbo perdiculari,</hi> by the Lowſie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, which made a modern Poet ſing:</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:121276:40"/>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Rex ille Philippus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tot populis, Terriſque potens, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Tyrannus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Occidit a foedo roſus grege Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi culorum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carnificieſque ſuos miſerando corpore pavit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vivens, atque videns, &amp; propria funera planxit.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Nor was it any other then a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of Divine vengeance from an angry Deity; which ſome imputed to his baſe Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Lechery; ſome gave out it was a Judgement for making away his Son <hi>Don Carlos;</hi> others affirm'd it to be a Judgement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon him, for the Duke <hi>d'Alva's</hi> Tyranny over the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians;</hi> others, that it was for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving <hi>Portugal</hi> of her lawfull Heir. But moſt men did gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally concur in this opinion, That
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121276:41"/>it was a puniſhment ſent from Heaven, for that Ocean of Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican blood that was ſpilt by him, to poſſeſs themſelves with their Mines of Gold and Silver. Oh that ſordid Lucre ſhould prompt a man to the effuſion of ſo much blood! when it might have been procured with far more honour and renown to the Conquerors, if otherwiſe ordered, and they themſelves have been free from ſuch a barbarous imputation: but what would you have? or what can you expect otherwiſe? for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Engliſh Proverb, <hi>They muſt needs go that the Devil drives;</hi> and he doubtleſs hath been the Helliſh <hi>Machiavil</hi> that hath endoctrinated them in moſt of their politick Deſigns; but no doubt he that ſet them forward, will, give them their due reward.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121276:41"/>'Tis impoſſible ſo much vill any as hath been acted by that Nation, ſhould be for ever unpuniſhed; to think ſo, were to accuſe the Supream Governor of all things, of the higheſt injuſtice; but far be it from any man to harbour ſuch a thought. Time will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce much, and then our eyes may ſee what we are now aſſured of will happen, unleſs by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance, and a deluge of penetential tears, they waſh their hands from that deluge of humane blood they have poured out; but it muſt not be their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in a coat of hair, or their bare-foot pilgrimages, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted abſteniouſneſs, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Superſtitious Ceremonies that are uſed among them; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be of a contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. But now a little more of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121276:42"/>their nature and diſpoſition, and we have done.</p>
            <p>The auſterity of the Spaniards temper, and the ſeverity and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected arrogancy of their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, renders them odious to all other Nations, when as an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and yet handſom deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would make them far more acceptable. They are ſo addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to lazineſs and ſloth, that their idleneſs is grown common, even to a Proverb. Now every School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy that is ſubject to the laſh, can tell them, <hi>Otium peſtis Reipub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae:</hi> Idleneſs is the moth or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the Commonwealth; and if this Caterpiller continue long upon the boughs of the Olive, it will leave it as inconſiderable and mean in the judgement of all the world, as they now would fain induce them to believe it
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121276:42"/>mighty and magnificent. They are the very Harpies of the earth, or like that roaring Lion, pace the circumference of the Globe, ſeeking whom they may devour; for whereſoever they can once get admiſſion, they caſt about by all poſſible means to ruinate and deſtroy the inhabitants, uſing all artifices, and picking quarrels to that end and purpoſe; So that that <hi>Maronian</hi> Dyſtich may very well agree with their practiſes, which ſaith:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Armati Terram exercent, ſemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que recentes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Convectare juvat praedas, &amp; vivere rapto.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>They are naturally prone to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect all they have any acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with, how ſlender ſoever it be; an argument of a depraved
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121276:43"/>diſpoſition, and corrupt nature; and as proud as <hi>Lucifer</hi> the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Angel: but we know the uſual fortune that attends ſuch haughty mindes:</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>tolluntur in altum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ut lapſu graviore ruant.</hi>—</l>
            </q>
            <p>They are exalted and lifted up on high, that their fall may be the greater. They are alſo infinitely addicted to ſelf-love; then which there is no greater enemy to true friendſhip which is the bond that ties human ſociety together, and makes man to be what he was born for, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creature. They are arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant to their inferiors, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Superiors, which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues them to be made up of an ignoble allay, and ſprung of a dunghil brood, verifying the old ſaying:</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:121276:43"/>
            <q>
               <hi>Aſperius nihil eſt humiſi, quum ſurg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in altum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Catalaunians</hi> are naturally paſſionate, impatient of labor, and addicted to Theft beyond meaſure. The <hi>Arragonians</hi> are factious, mutinous, and ſubject to rebellion. Thoſe of <hi>Andaluzia</hi> are of a cruel temper, drunkards; a vice that the Egyptians did ſo much abhorre, that when they found any of their ſervants over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with this Exceſs, they brought them forth, ſhewing them to their children, that they might learn in their young years to avoid the Crime in their old age. Now ſhould you ſee any of them in this ſwiniſh condition, you would take him to be an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated ſop, that is newly ſprung out of a pot of Ale in a froſty
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121276:44"/>morning; which makes them have ſuch red-coated faces, and ſuch fiery noſes, that you might try a yong Eagle by their bloody beak; you might ſoon underſtand by their complexion what broth they love: 'tis well that they cannot compaſs a meſs of our <hi>Ceres</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-gruel, for if they could, we ſhould ſcarce hear of the natural death of one of them once in an Age; for they would all quickly ſwim to their graves in a drunken fit: beſides, they are ſo avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that they learn Geometry onely to meaſure the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their houſhold bread, that they may know to a haires breadth how much of it is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in their abſence; and ſhould you chance to be invited to a Collation or Dinner among them you muſt feed ſparingly, or elſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121276:44"/>it may be finde the Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb verified, <hi>To have roaſt meat given you, and be beaten with the ſpit:</hi> Not a leg of a Capon that you cut but you ham-ſtring the poor man that invites you, and he had as live ſee you drink his own blood, as ſup up the gravy. And yet this proud imperious fellow will (out of oſtentation, if he chance to have a fowl to dinner) ſtrew the feathers at the door, to ſhew all Paſſengers that they have had noble fare: but this you muſt note proceeds from the want of victuals among them. 'Tis the general diſpoſition of them all, to believe what they fancy, more than what they either do, or indeed can really act, and eſpecially of the <hi>Portugeſe;</hi> nor will he deny it, <hi>Portugalli dicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſe niti eo potius, quod ſe eſſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121276:45"/>putant, quam eo, quam revera ſunt.</hi> And yet what are theſe <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals?</hi> a rude rabble or pack of ſlaves; for the number of them in ſome places are very near as great, if not more then the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants; And there are very few places where there is ſo little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction among them; for they ſcarce make any difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men and beaſt, and they are both ſold in the market at an equal rate, ſo that they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be term'd a Crew of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, or Pagans, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their pretended zeal to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. But that is but a fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to ſet off their vill any the better, a meer ceremony among them, and indeed ſo much cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that it hath almoſt eaten out the ſubſtance of Religion, Bible, Alchoran, Talmud, or Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121276:45"/>Legion, all's one; Religion ſerves but for a meer Stratagem, and their Prieſts, that were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained (or at leaſt ſhould be) to exorciſe devils, are the greateſt fiends, and ſhould, if rightly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, be caſt out themſelves. But now, as to the foundation of their imagined <hi>Grandeza,</hi> that they have brought their Government unto, as they imagine: The very form thereof is very unpleaſing to a ſubject, for they had rather rule by fear than love, and where ſhe acquires any of the latter, it is drawn as a thread through the eye of a needle out of the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of fear: it being one of their State-maxims, That Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience proceeding from ſuch a love, is the ſureſt and ſafeſt, in regard that Fear being the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt careful Governeſs
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121276:46"/>of our paſſions, ſways all the reſt with more power and controul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and keeps them ſtill in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and ſo conſequently makes as good ſubjects, as it did Gods at firſt.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Primus in orbe Deos fecit timor</hi>—</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fear firſt created Gods.—</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Nay farther, the chief and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Miniſters they employ, are ſo much for their private lucre, and ſelf-intereſt, (which moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly proves the deſtruction of a Kingdom) that it is grown to a Proverb, <hi>Some of them gnaw, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eat, and ſome devour, where they are deputed to ſignorize and govern.</hi> But, now 'tis time to change our ſubject, and to be a little more milde in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and Character.</p>
            <p>In this fore-going Diſcourſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121276:46"/>you have ſeen their moſt hainous Vices, cruel Plots, helliſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and barbarous Enterprizes; as alſo their imperious Mindes, proud and haughty Spirits, their baſe Tempers and Diſpoſitions, and their depraved Natures, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Tenets, and wicked Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms; Now that we may not be thought to be altogether made up of ſpleen and choler, and to have dipt our pen in <hi>aqua-fortis,</hi> or vinegar, we ſhall take a ſhort ſurvey of their Virtues, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Qualifications, to the end we may demonſtrate unto you that they have ſomewhat among them, which may merit commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation as well as condemnation. And firſt, the Soyl is healthful, having for a long time a conſtant ſerene Ayr, which made the Prince of Greek Poets, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121276:47"/>other Authors place the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſian fields</hi> here; for there are no groſs, caligmous vapors riſing up from Bogs or Fens, but there are moſt refreſhing, ſoft <hi>Zephyres</hi> or Breezes, that pierce the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumambient Air, and enliven both man and beaſt; nay, Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that uſe to traverſe thoſe Seas, can tell when they approach the coaſts of <hi>Spain</hi> by the odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerous ſmel of Roſemary, &amp; other Aromatick Vegetals that grow there up and down the common fields, and perfume the Air with their fragrancy: She is not parcht with ſuch exceſſive heat as <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> nor ſhaken with ſuch impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous windes as <hi>France,</hi> nor toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſuch earthquakes as <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> nor nipt and pincht by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numming thumbs of Winter, as <hi>Holland, Swethland,</hi> and ſeveral
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121276:47"/>other Regions; but enjoys a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and temperate Air. <hi>Spain</hi> abounds with the moſt generous Wines, and the beſt Oyls; as alſo the beſt Fruits, as Figs, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, Almonds, Orenges, Lemons, and Pomegrannets, and all other kinde of Vegetables, as Herbs, Roots, and Flowers. Beſides her bowels are richly furniſhed with Mettals, as Iron, Steel, Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver, and Gold. She produceth good Silk, Flax, an excellent Wooll, though they are behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us for that commodity.</p>
            <p>Now for that generous Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal the Horſe, ſhe ſurpaſſeth all Countreys; for their <hi>Cordovan Gjnnets</hi> excel thoſe of <hi>Turkey</hi> for fierceneſs; thoſe of <hi>Barbary</hi> for their light feet, or nimble heels, as we term it; and thoſe of <hi>Italy</hi> in comlineſs of proportion. Her
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121276:48"/>ſtately Fabricks, Structures, and Cities, are as numerous as ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; which occaſioned the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Quien no ha viſto Sevilla, non ha viſto Maravilla: Quien no ha viſto Lisboa?, no ha viſto coſa boa.</hi> He that ne're ſaw <hi>Sevil,</hi> ne're ſaw a miracle; and he that ne're ſaw <hi>Lisbon,</hi> ne're ſaw any thing that was rare; but the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the words in the Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, is far more harmonious than in the Engliſh Dialect. To prove which, I need mention but one, and that is the Monaſtery of <hi>St. Laurence,</hi> near the <hi>Eſcurial,</hi> which for matter and form is not to be parallel'd. <hi>Claudian</hi> breaks out into an Elogium of her, which concludes thus:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Dives equis, frugum facilis, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſa metallis.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:121276:48"/>
            <p>The patience of the Spaniard is commendable; their valor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; their fidelity very ſignal, which was the reaſon that <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> us'd to have a Guard of them, and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> a Band of <hi>Biſcayners</hi> or <hi>Cantabrians</hi> about him. In their Military diſcipline they are admirable, very ſtrict and ſevere, and obedient to their Commanders; as may appear by that Spaniſh Centinel, who was found dead in the morning in a tower upon the Cittadel of <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp,</hi> with his musket in his hand, in a defenſive poſture, &amp; ſtanding on his legs upright, like one that was alive and in health to their ſeeming, yet all frozen. Beſides, they are infinitely carefull of their National Honor, and very induſtrious to promote it. For their Diſcoveries of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121276:49"/>they have had great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and rendred themſelves fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thereby. And though they have received vaſt heaps of gold and ſilver from the <hi>Americans,</hi> in requital whereof, that they might not be altogether ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they received Chriſtianity, and we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e civiliz'd by them, when as before the Savages did reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bruit beaſts more than ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal men.</p>
            <p>It was the Spaniſh Navigation that firſt confuted that erroneous opinion, that there were no ſuch perſons in <hi>eſſe,</hi> as the <hi>Antipodes;</hi> when as be ore there was a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop impriſon'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying this now uncontrovertible Tenet, which is underſtood al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt by every plebeian. The Friars in the Weſt, and the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> firſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121276:49"/>planted Chriſtian Religion, and cultivated thoſe parts, and made a fruitful vineyard of them, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing them in the Laver of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; nay, it is credibly repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that one ſingle Franciſcan Frier did chriſten 400000 of them. And though the Proverb hath it, <hi>Eſpania las Armas, Italia lapluma. Spain</hi> is more for the pike, then the pen, yet they have produc'd ſome famous lights of the Church, as <hi>Fulgentius, Iſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, Paulus Oroſius, Juſtinian,</hi> and others, and ſome Rabbies, though of different ſect, yet may they have a place in the <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi> of learned men, as Rabbi <hi>David Chimcho,</hi> Rabbi <hi>Abenez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> and Rabbi <hi>Maſes,</hi> and more that might be mention'd.</p>
            <p>Now for eminent Doctors in the Civil Law, ſhe hath brought up
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121276:50"/>no ſmall number, as <hi>Alvarus Valaſcus Goveaneus,</hi> that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and approv'd of for the beſt, and trueſt interpreter that ever commented upon <hi>Juſtinian, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixtus</hi> the third, and <hi>Pinellus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Phyſick ſhe hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd many that have bin very eminent, as <hi>Garcias ab Horto, Averroes</hi> of <hi>Cordova, Chriſtopher a Vega, Avicenna</hi> of <hi>Sevil,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Nor hath ſhe bin deſtitute of Philoſophers, witneſs <hi>Seneca</hi> who tranſcended, and ſurpaſs't all his Predeceſſors and Poſterity hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto in precepts of morality, &amp; many more that might be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd. She hath flouriſht with ſtore of Poets that deſerv'd the Bays, as <hi>Silius, Italicus, Lucan,</hi> and ſeveral others that might be ſpecified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> the Rhetorician was an
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121276:50"/>off-ſpring of their own, who was famous for his tenacious memory and ſeveral famous Hiſtorians, as well as Orators, <hi>Juſtinus</hi> the great, <hi>Trogus Pomperus, Ludovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Vives, Pomponius Mela Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Columella,</hi> and <hi>Fabius Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilianus.</hi> All which, have added very much to the Republick of Literature, and bin famous for their ſeveral works now extant: And that you may not think Learning to be a qualification that men are onely adorned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, you ſhall find it ſhine in the contrary ſex, for they can boaſt of one <hi>Aloyſia Sigea,</hi> a famous female, <hi>Pallas Alcera,</hi> a ſecond <hi>Minerva,</hi> who was excellently verſ'd in five ſeveral languages, and thoſe that are the radices of all others, as Latine, Greek, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, Syriack, and Chaldaick:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121276:51"/>and ſome of the epiſtles that <hi>Paul</hi> the third wrote to this <hi>Toledo</hi> vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, are extent to this very day. That her confines extend incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, wil appear by this, that there are but 360<hi rend="sup">d</hi> in the Zodiack, and <hi>Portugal</hi> herſelf is thought to take up 200. Now it muſt neceſſarily follow, that her policy &amp; prudence in governing ſo many ſquandred kingdoms, &amp; ſo great a number of inhabitants, of ſeveral humours, conſtitutions and tempers, muſt needs be great. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> may <hi>imperare,</hi> but the miracle is, how he makes them <hi>parere;</hi> 'tis not ſo great a wonder that he governs them, as that he makes themobey, when as we all know that the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar are very apt to be rebellious, and raiſe a mutiny in one ſingle countrey, and yet he makes mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of people, and thoſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121276:51"/>countreys, bow to his Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And as ſhe is famous for her Government and Policy, ſhe is alſo eminent for the number of Princes that ſhe hath brought forth, &amp; beſtow'd upon other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, as well as thoſe that have ſway'd the Spaniſh Scepter; and firſt ſhe produced <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who firſt founded the Spaniſh Monarchy, by matching with <hi>Donna Iſabella,</hi> queen of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the II. who was tearm'd <hi>Philip the Prudent,</hi> by a Parlament in <hi>Spain,</hi> &amp; afterwards ſolemnly confirm'd by a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory at <hi>Rome:</hi> Beſides, ſhe hath brought forth Princes to other nations, as <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the I. &amp; the firſt Emperor noted for Morality and Virtue, who rebuilt and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up the tottering Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: And <hi>Trajan</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121276:52"/>who had as great a ſhare of Piety, as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> had of Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as alſo the Emperor <hi>Hadri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Firſt, who was an Infant of <hi>Spain;</hi> a Prince, who for all Virtues and Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations ſuitable to, and neceſſary for one of his dignity, came ſhort of none of his Predeceſſors.</p>
            <p>To conclude, and draw to a period: The Spaniard is very much to be commended for his Policy, Prudence, and deliberate Conſultations, for his Patience, Gravity, and admirable Choler; his noble, and liberal Diſpoſition; his Valor, Magnanimity, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and height of Spirit: As for <hi>Spain</hi> her ſelf, ſhe may be term'd <hi>The Exchequer of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> and the Nurſe of ſtout Champions, who exceeds in Men and Mines, and Arts as well as
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121276:52"/>Arms. Her Kings are the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt arm'd Monarchs in the world, who have as many Kingdoms as ſome have Provinces; as many Fleets, as ſome have Ships; as many Viceroys, as ſome Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals; and as many Capitains by Sea and Land, as others have pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Soldiers. Fortune her ſelf may be call'd the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Wife, who hath brought with her ſuch vaſt Treaſures for her Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And thus having given you a taſte of her Vices and Vertues, Power and Weakneſs, Perfection and Imperfection, I lay down my Quill, being come to my <hi>Ne ultra.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:53"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books to be ſold by</hi> Nath Brook <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Cornhil.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THe Accompliſht Cook, the Myſtery of the whole Art of Cookery revealed in a more eaſie and perfect Method then hath been publiſht in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; expert and ready ways for the dreſſing of Fleſh, Fowl and Fiſh, the raiſing of Paſtes, the beſt directions for all manner of Kickſhaws, and the moſt poinant Sauces, with the terms of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and Sewing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Robert May,</hi> in the time of his attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on ſeveral perſons of Honor.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>J. Cleaveland</hi> Revived: Poems, Orations, Epiſtles, and other of his Genuine Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pieces: A ſecond Impreſſion with many Additions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Exquiſite Letters of
<pb facs="tcp:121276:53"/>Maſter <hi>Robert Loveday,</hi> the late admired Tranſlator of the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the famed Romance <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> for the perpetuaring his memory: publiſht by his dear Brother, Mr. <hi>A. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Englands</hi> Worthies: Select Lives of the moſt Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great to the death of <hi>O. Cromwel</hi> late Protector: By <hi>W. Winſtanley</hi> Gent. An excellent Piece.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Scales of Commerce and Trade: the Myſtery reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to Traffick with a Debitor or Creditor, for Merchants Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts after the Italian way, and eaſieſt Method; As alſo a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Architecture, and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation as to all the Charges of Building: By <hi>T. Wilsford</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>William Clowes</hi> his Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Obſervations for thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:121276:54"/>are burned with flames of Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder; as alſo for the curing of wounds, and of the <hi>Lues venerea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Moor's</hi> Arithmetick, the ſecond Edition much refined, and diligently cleared from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer miſtakes of the Preſs. A Work containing the whole Art of Arithmetick, as well in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as Species. Likewiſe,</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Exercitatio Elleiptica Nova:</hi> Or, a new Mathematical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation on the Oval Figure, called an <hi>Elleipſis;</hi> together with the two firſt Books of <hi>Midorgius</hi> his Conicks Analiz'd, and made ſo plain, that the Doctrine of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Sections may be eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; a Work much deſired, and never before publiſht in the Engliſh tongue: By <hi>Jonas Moor,</hi> late of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:54"/>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:121276:55"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Nathaniel Brooke, featuring an angel holding a large feather or quill</figDesc>
                  <p>N B</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
